Finding Aid for Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (University of Michigan) records, 1961-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (University of Michigan) records 1961-[ongoing] 1972-2004
University of Michigan. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching.
Center devoted to assisting faculty in the task of providing effective instruction, including evaluation and research. Series in the record group include Budget, Correspondence, Topical, and Grants; files related to the administration and research and educational activities of the center, and of its directors Stanford Ericksen and Wilbert J. McKeachie.
921093 Bimu C537 2
24 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the Center (donor no. 7926 ) in 1991. Periodic additions to this record group are expected.
The collection is open for research.
One of the first of its kind in the country, the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT) at the University of Michigan was established in 1962 by the Board of Regents after a faculty committee recommended:
1) That the University of Michigan create a Center on University Teaching with the broad aim of providing maximum assistance to the faculty of the University in the task of providing effective instruction of the highest quality; and
2) That it be of prime importance that the Center be created at the outset as an institution devoted to the encouragement of educational excellence. (Box 3, Folder: History #2, "Regents Proceedings")
CRLT staff members spend much of their time providing services to the university community. Among the most important programs and services of the Center are Instructor Designed Questionnaires (IDQ), which facilitate student ratings of courses; Evaluations and Examinations, a scoring service for both the IDQs and objective examinations such as foreign language tests, entrance examinations, and machine-gradable examinations from various university courses; instructional workshops and colloquia on matters of interest to teachers; teaching assistant training workshops; the Faculty Development Fund (FDF), a supplement to the base budget of the Center which awards grants to selected faculty in order to encourage new directions in teaching; computer consulting, particularly with regard to the use of computers in the classroom; and program evaluation and consulting. As of 1997, the Center had developed the leading program in the country for training foreign teaching assistants.
Although primarily concerned with service, the Center's staff have undertaken many research projects. Among the more important have been student development studies of the Inteflex, Pilot, and Residential College programs; studies of computer usage in the Chemistry and English departments; meta-analyses of the effectiveness of computers in teaching, of the factors affecting student evaluations of faculty, and of the use of personalized system instruction; and research on strategies and motivational factors which affect teaching and learning.
Administratively, the Center has always reported to the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs. Its staff members are primarily comprised of professors from units within the university with joint appointments in the Center and their home unit, and research scientists hired to oversee research projects and various services provided by the Center. Initially the Center was advised by the University of Michigan Faculty Senate Subcommittee on the Improvement of Instruction. Later, an advisory committee was established of faculty interested in the work of CRLT. One of the tasks to which the Advisory Committee devotes a good deal of time is approving requests from the FDF. Policy matters are primarily decided by the Center director and an elected executive committee of CRLT staff members.
Due to worsening economic conditions and as part of the move to a "smaller but better" university in the early 1980s, CRLT was one of several units subject to review and budget reduction. Its budget was reduced by 30% in 1981 and a year later the Center participated in a university-wide budget cut of 5%. The Evaluations and Examinations office was closed and its director released, although CRLT continues to provide scoring services. Yearly Provost Office budget allocations are supplemented by various grants, requests and donations.
CRLT is a central administrative unit reporting to the provost and serving all 19 schools and colleges of the University of Michigan Ann Arbor Campus. It is also available to service the Dearborn and Flint Campuses.
As a department CRLT recognizes that undergraduates, graduates, instructors, faculty, administration and professional staff represent differing interests, interests which coexist to define the culture of the University of Michigan. The stated goal is to foster an environment of cooperation between these various subcultures and between the various disciplines to contribute to the excellence of the university.
The Center's URL is http://www.umich.edu/~crltmich/.
CRLT Directors
1962-1972 Stanford Ericksen
1972-1975 James Kulik (Acting)
1975-1983 Wilbert McKeachie
1983-1993 Donald Brown
1993- Constance E. Cook
The records of CRLT document the administration of the unit and its programmatic activities including funding of faculty research projects. The records are divided into five series: Budgets, Correspondence, Topical, Grants, and Workshops and Seminars. The majority of the materials are from the period 1972-2004.
The CRLT records have been received in various accessions and installments and housed in sequentially numbered boxes reflecting the order in which the accessions were received. This finding aid reflects the intellectual organization of the record group. Series and subseries received in multiple accessions are described and listed as units even though they may be stored in
Subjects:
College teachers--Ratings of.; College teaching--Research.; Computers.; Learning, Psychology of.; Learning--Research.; Motivation in education.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching.
Contributors:
Ericksen, Stanford C. (Stanford Clark), 1911-; McKeachie, Wilbert James, 1921-
- Budgets 1962-1993, 2 linear feet
  The Budgets series (2 linear foot) is arranged chronologically (1962-1993) and is comprised mostly of budget sheets and correspondence. The materials can be used to study projects undertaken, staffing changes, and how CRLT reacted to the budget cuts of the early 1980s. In addition, the files are one of the few sources of information on the first ten years of the center's existence. [Box 1, 15]
  - 1962/63-1985/86, 25 folders (Box 1)
  - 1986-1990, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - 1990-1993, 3 folders (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 3 linear feet
  The Correspondence series (3 linear feet) consists of volumes of outgoing correspondence (1964; 1972-1984; "early 1980s" and 1994) arranged chronologically. Early letters are written by Stan Ericksen in his capacities as director and later, as senior research scientist. There are also letters from other CRLT staff and directors, including Drs. Kulik and McKeachie. The correspondence sheds light on major activities of the center, and the role it played in assisting other universities to set up similar centers. The researcher should note that, on occasion, copies of minutes of staff and executive committee meetings are included in the volumes of correspondence. [Box 1-2, 13]
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - July 1975-June 1976 (Box 2)
  - July 1976-June 1977 (Box 2)
  - July 1977-June 1978 (Box 2)
  - 1978 (Box 2)
  - July 1978-June 1979 (Box 2)
  - July 1979-June 1980 (Box 2)
  - July 1980-June 1981 (2 vols.) (Box 2)
  - 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - McKeachie, Wilbert 1993 outgoing, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Brown, Don 1993 outgoing, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Brown, Don, Early 1980s
    - A-P, 16 folders (Box 13)
    - Prentice-Hall (Box 13)
    - R-W, 6 folders (Box 13)
    - XYZ (Box 13)
- Topical 1955-1995, 4 linear feet
  The Topical series (4 linear feet) is divided into three overlapping time spans (reflecting separate accessions) and thereunder is arranged alphabetically. CRLT did not produce an annual report until 1975; for information on the its various projects and activities prior to that time, the researcher should consult the Activities Inventories file. The administrative life of the center is well documented in the minutes found in the files of the Advisory and Executive Committees and in the Staff Meetings folder. Use of computers in classrooms around the university can be studied from materials in the Computer file, and the Wolverine Fund folders. The fund supplied grants to assist with computer-aided instruction. The folders include interesting correspondence and grant proposals. The Reviews files contain insightful documents on the reviews conducted to determine whether the CRLT budget was to be cut. The report of the 1983 committee includes a helpful history. Other materials related to the history of CRLT, especially the early years, are found in the History folders. The Vice President for Academic Affairs files are comprised mostly of correspondence on a variety of topics, including the budget, computers, and teaching assistant training. Also of interest are materials related to the orientation of new faculty and graduate student instructors, and papers written by the CRLT staff about a variety of education and teaching issues. [Box 3-4, 14-15, 18-19]
  - 1955-1983
    - Activities Inventories 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - Advisory/Policy Committee 1970-1984 (Box 3)
      (mostly minutes and membership lists)
    - American Association for Higher Education 1980 (Box 3)
    - Brown, Don 1978-1981 (Box 3)
    - Clippings 1962-1975 (Box 3)
      (university publications and the Ann Arbor News)
    - Computers 1971-1984 (Box 3)
    - Director Search 1973 (Box 3)
    - English Composition Board 1980 (Box 3)
    - Evaluation and Examinations Office 1955-1982 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee 1973-1983 (mostly minutes) (Box 3)
    - Faculty Associates Program 1976-1980 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Development 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Instructional Workshops 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Surveys of LS&A and Engineering 1971 (CRLT proposal for) (Box 3)
    - Grants 1975-1982 (Box 3)
    - History 1961-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Innovative Teaching Fund 1972 (Box 3)
    - International Business Machines 1965 (Box 3)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of 1965-1974 (Box 3)
    - Off-Campus Housing, President's Commission on 1965 (Box 3)
      (minutes of May 26 meeting-Ericksen as consultant)
    - Personnel Committee 1976-1982 (Box 3)
    - Planning 1979 (Box 3)
      (Memorandum of Understanding 1977-1978 to 1980-1981 Planning Period)
    - Reviews
      - 1981 (Box 3)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Staff Meetings 1975-1982 (minutes) (Box 3)
    - Statewide Expansion 1966 (Box 3)
    - Student Ratings of Teaching Effectiveness 1981 (Box 3)
    - Study Skills 1984 (Box 3)
    - Teaching Assistant Training 1971-1980 (Box 3)
    - Teaching Quality 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Technology in Teaching and Learning, Task Force on 1981, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Telecommunications and Film Technology 1971 (Box 3)
    - Vice President for Academic Affairs, Office of
      - Davis, Carolyne 1975-1979 (Box 3)
      - Frye, Billy 1980-1984 (Box 3)
      - Holbrook, Robert 1981-1983 (Box 3)
      - Rhodes, Frank 1974-1976 (Box 3)
      - Sauve, Robert 1979-1982 (Box 3)
      - Shapiro, Harold 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      - Smith, Allan 1972 (Box 3)
    - Wolverine Fund 1968, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1980-1995
    - Advisory Task Force 1993-1994 (Box 14)
    - Alumni (Box 14)
    - Common Art 1984 (Box 14)
    - CRLT Background & History (Box 14)
    - Current Programs 1993 (Box 14)
    - Directors Meetings 1986-1993 (Box 14)
    - Evaluator's Report 1993 (Box 14)
    - Executive Committee 1980-1993, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Faculty Development Fund, 1984-85 (Box 14)
    - Faculty Handbook 1985 (Box 14)
    - Faculty Identified Problems in Clinical Dentistry (Box 14)
    - Funding Proposals 1986 (Box 14)
    - Job Description For Program Manager 1995 (Box 14)
    - M4 Combined Reports 1976-1980 (Box 14)
    - Medical School Senior Interviews 1983 (Box 14)
    - Memos to Provost 1989-1993 (Box 14)
    - Photographs (Box 14)
    - Policy Committee 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Program Review, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Quarterly Report on Sponsored Research 1985-1988 (Box 14)
    - Questionnaires, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Report of the Subcommittee on Pedagogy 1991 (Box 15)
    - Report on Objectives, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Reports 1-35 1975-1981, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Review Committee 1983 (Box 15)
    - Samples of Research Tools, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Search for Coordinator of Multicultural Teaching & Learning Services 1994 (Box 15)
    - Staff (Box 15)
    - Staff Meetings 1973-1992, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Staff Retreat 1993 (Box 15)
    - Workshops, Content 1985-1986 (Box 15)
  - 1975-2004
    - Annual Reports 1975/76-2002/03, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - CRLT History, written 1962-2001 (Box 18)
    - CRLT List of Publications (1966-1976), Memo to Faculty (Box 18)
    - CRLT Programs
      - CRLT Miscellaneous Program Brochures 2003-2004 (Box 18)
      - CRLT Program Information Sheets 2003 versions (Box 18)
      - CRLT Theatre Program Materials (includes 7 minute VHS video on the program, 2002) (Box 18)
    - CRLT Staff Articles/Papers
      - Barnett, M. (1971). An Introduction to FOIL Programming in MTS. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (Box 18)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (no date). Guidance for Instructors concerning Class Discussions about War in Iraq. (Box 18)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (2001 October 5). Guidance for UM Instructors Leading Class Discussions on the Tragedy of September 11, 2001. (Box 18)
      - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (1994 March). Guidelines for Evaluating Teaching. (Box 18)
      - Cook, C.E. (date?) The Role of a Teaching Center in Curricular Reform. To Improve the Academy, 19, 217-231. (Box 18)
      - Cook, C.E., Kaplan, M., Nidiffer, J., & Wright, M.C. (2001 November) Preparing Future Faculty Faster: A Crash Course Guides Students to the Professoriate AAHE Bulletin, pp. 3-7. (Box 18)
      - Cook, C.E. & Sorcinelli, M.D. (1999 March). Building Multiculturalism into Teaching-Development Programs. AAHE Bulletin, pp.3-6. (Box 18)
      - Cook, C.E. & Sorcinelli, M.D. (2002 April 26). The Importance of Teaching Centers. The Chronicle of Higher Education, p. B21. (Box 18)
      - Ericksen, S. C. (1973). Learning Theory and the Law School Classroom. Council on Legal Education for Professional Responsibility (CLEPR), VI (4). (Box 18)
      - Kaplan, M., Mets, L.A., and Cook, C.E. (1995 Winter). Questions Frequently Asked About Student Ratings Forms: Summary of Research Findings. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (Box 18)
      - Kardia, D. (1998). Becoming a Multicultural Faculty Developer: Reflections from the Field. To Improve the Academy, 17. (Box 18)
      - Kardia, D., Bierwert, C., Cook, C.E., Miller, A.T., & Kaplan, M. (2002 Jan/February). Discussing the Unfathomable: Classroom-based Responses to Tragedy. Change, pp. 19-21. (Box 18)
      - Kulik, J.A., & Kulik, C.C. (1997 November). College Teaching. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (Box 18)
      - Kulik, J.A., Kulik, C., & Carmichael, K. (1974). The Keller Plan in Science Teaching. Science, 83, 379-383. (Box 18)
      - Miller, D.M., & Brown, D. R. (no date). Preparation for College Teaching in a Research Dominated Reward System. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (Box 18)
      - Saunders, S., & Kardia, D. (1998). Creating Inclusive College Classrooms. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. (Box 18)
    - Department Chair Orientation, List of Registrants 1979 (Box 18)
    - Faculty Development
      - Building Multiculturalism Into Faculty Development Summer Institute Materials June 21-24, 1998 (Box 18)
      - Engineering 100 Faculty Workshop Materials May 16, 2001 (Box 18)
      - Critical Assessment of Learning: Coordinating, Communicating, and Meeting Expectations Presentation for School of Nursing Preceptor Appreciation Day May 21, 2001 (Box 18)
      - Effective Team Teaching: Building and Sustaining Collaborations That Work for Faculty and Their Students Event Materials May 13, 2002 (Box 18)
    - Faculty: New Faculty Orientation Agendas 1977-2003 (Box 18)
    - Faculty: New Faculty Orientation Materials 1976-1983, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Fortieth Anniversary Celebration of CRLT November 8, 2002 (Box 18)
    - Graduate Student Instructor Orientation Materials (GSIO) 1980-2002, 26 folders (Box 18)
    - Graduate Student Instructor (Engineering) Orientation Materials (EGSIO) 1996-2004, 9 folders (Box 19)
    - Graduate Student Instructor Training, Program Development Correspondence 1972-1987 (Box 19)
    - Publicity and Media Coverage 1994-2004 (Box 19)
    - Reports
      - College of Engineering and CRLT Faculty Development Program undated (Box 19)
      - CRLT External Evaluation November 15, 1993 (Box 19)
      - Proposal for Foreign Teaching Assistant Training in LS&A 1986 (Box 19)
      - The Summer Training Program for Foreign Teaching Assistants: A Request for Partial Funding 1985 (Box 19)
      - Review of CRLT Programs and Performance 1983 (Box 19)
    - Visitors to CRLT 1973-1992 (Box 19)
    - Visitors to CRLT, Correspondence 1973-1992 (Box 19)
- Grants 1965-2000, 13 linear feet
  The Grants series (13 linear feet) consists of correspondence, applications, evaluations and reports relating to grants awarded by CRLT. The series contains three subseries: Faculty Development Fund, Instructional Development Fund, and Miscellaneous Grants. The Faculty Development Fund (FDF) subseries concerns grants awarded through that fund from 1977 to 1999. Through FDF the Center awards up to $6,000 to individual faculty members for smaller projects and up to $10,000 to departments, programs, and groups of faculty. These grants generally support ambitious, relatively large faculty projects. The subseries is arranged chronologically, by the year the grant was awarded and then alphabetically by the name of the professor receiving the grant. [Box 4-6, 9-12, 16-17, 19-22]
  The Instructional Development Fund (IDF) concerns grants awarded by that fund between 1973 and 2000. These projects tended to be more modest than those funded by the FDF. The Instructional Development subseries is organized by year, then alphabetically within each year by the name of the professor receiving the grant.
  The Miscellaneous Grants subseries covers grants awarded from 1965 to 2000. These grants were funded through the Instructional Development Fund, the Wolverine Fund, or the Special Projects Fund. The Miscellaneous Grants subseries is arranged alphabetically by the name of the department receiving the award for the years 1965-1973. After 1973, the Miscellaneous Grants are arranged first by grant, then chronologically by the year the grant was awarded, and then alphabetically by the name of the professor receiving the grant.
  The Grants series includes materials only for projects that received grants, not for applications that were denied grants, before 1998. Some of the unfunded grant applications were included for materials after 1998.
  - Faculty Development Fund
    - 1977
      - Dean's Recommendations (Box 5)
      - Proposals (Box 5)
      - Support Letters (Box 5)
      - Baird, John; Speech (Box 5)
      - Becker, Alton; Linguistics (Box 5)
      - Berry, Mary; Asian Studies (Box 5)
      - Blumenfeld, Phyllis; Education (Box 5)
      - Boley, Richard; Accounting (Box 5)
      - Braunstier, Harriet and John Hansen; Psychology/ Computer Science (Box 5)
      - Brazer, Harvey; Economics (Box 5)
      - Brilliant, Lawrence; Public Health (Box 5)
      - Brumfiel, Charles; Math (Box 5)
      - Burdi, Alphonse; Medical School (Box 5)
      - Crawford, David; Music (Box 5)
      - Edwards, Mary; Residential College (Box 5)
      - Fisher, Leslie, Anatomy (Box 5)
      - Fabian, Hans; German (Box 5)
      - Gies, Thomas; Business Administration (Box 5)
      - Gill, Steven; Education (Box 5)
      - Hierich, Max; Sociology (Box 5)
      - Hopwood, Nancy; Medical School (Box 5)
      - Kane, Gordon; Physics (Box 5)
      - Kirkpatrick, Diane; History of Art (Box 5)
      - Low, Bobbi; Natural Resources (Box 5)
      - Mack, Dorothy and Peter Klaver; Humanities (Box 5)
      - Magrill, Rose and Constance Reinhart; Library Science (Box 5)
      - Mason, Conrad and David Gates; Natural Science (Box 5)
      - Nadelman, Lorraine; Psychology (Box 5)
      - Olds, Clifton and Bret Waller; History of Art (Box 5)
      - Orlis, Louis; Ancient Near East History and Literature (Box 5)
      - Owens, Leslie; History (Box 5)
      - Park, Richard; Political Science (Box 5)
      - Pepe, Steven; Law (Box 5)
      - Rammuny, Raji and Margo MacInnis; Arabic Department of Near Eastern Studies (Box 5)
      - Reitman, Judith; Psychology (Box 5)
      - Richards, Tom; School of Management (Box 5)
      - Rollet, Ronald; Natural Resources (Box 5)
      - Schmerl, Rudolph; Education (Box 5)
      - Sell, Ranier; Humanities (Box 5)
      - Simon, Carl; Mathematics (Box 5)
      - Steneck, Nicholas; History (Box 5)
      - Studier, Eugene; Biology (Box 5)
      - Volz, Richard; Electrical and Computer Engineering (Box 5)
      - Warner, Katherine; Architecture and Urban Planning (Box 5)
      - Young, Marilyn; Residential College (Box 5)
    - 1978
      - Berkove, Lawrence; Interdisciplinary Studies (Box 5)
      - Boys, Donald; Physics (Box 5)
      - Baun, Mara (Box 6)
      - Dennison, Joseph; Dentistry (Box 6)
      - Dworin, Aaron and Jeoffrey Stross; Medical School (Box 6)
      - Erikson, Helen; Nursing (Box 6)
      - Froseth, James; Music (Box 6)
      - Hochster, Anita; English (Box 6)
      - Kleinman, Roberta; Natural Sciences (Box 6)
      - Kriewall, Timothy; Engineering (Box 6)
      - Kugler, Lawrence; Mathematics (Box 6)
      - Lavine, Steven; English (Box 6)
      - Maple, Frank; Social Work (Box 6)
      - Nyerges, Richard; Management (Box 6)
      - O'Neal, Robert; Medical School (Box 6)
      - Reider, David and Michael Hannum; Art (Box 6)
      - Rose, F.E.; Physics and Astronomy (Box 6)
      - Rosenthal, Marilyn; Sociology (Box 6)
      - Shapiro, Kenneth; Natural Resources (Box 6)
      - Taylor, Allen; Mathematics (Box 6)
      - Vinter, Robert; Social Work, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Support Letters (Box 6)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Atkins, D.E.; Electric and Computer Engineering (Box 6)
      - Berger, Carl; School of Education (Box 6)
      - Berardi, Rosemary; Pharmacy (Box 6)
      - Clipson, Colin; Art and Architecture, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Cohen, Ira; Pharmacy (Box 6)
      - Datsko, Joseph; Mechanical Engineering (Box 6)
      - Goldberg, Jack; Mathematics (Box 6)
      - Hirshhorn, Seth; Political Science (Box 6)
      - Hungerman, Ann; School of Education, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Jim, Lucia; Pharmacy (Box 6)
      - Kottak, Conrad; Anthropology (Box 6)
      - Margolis, Phillip; Medical School (Box 6)
      - Marquis, Stewart; Natural Resources (Box 6)
      - Marsh, William; Arts and Sciences (Box 6)
      - McGowan, Joan; Dentistry (Box 6)
      - Mudge, Trevor; College of Engineering (Box 7)
      - Olsen, Leslie; Humanities-English (Box 7)
      - Owen, George; Nutrition-Public Health (Box 7)
      - Van't Hull, Bernard; English (Box 7)
      - Wolf, Louis; Mechanical Engineering (Box 7)
    - 1980